C++ Coding Guidelines

Introduction

In terms of coding conventions, the style present within an existing source file should be favoured over the standards found below.

When a new source file is being created, the following coding conventions should be observed if creating a new file within the MAME core (src/emu and src/lib). If the source file is outside the core, deference can be given to a contributor’s preferred style, although it is strongly encouraged to code with the understanding that the file may need to be comprehensible by more than one person as time marches forward.

Definitions

Snake case

All lowercase letters with words separated by underscores: this_is_snake_case

Screaming snake case

All uppercase letters with words separated by underscores: SCREAMING_SNAKE_CASE

Camel case:

Lowercase initial letter, first letter of each subsequent word capitalised, with no separators between words: exampleCamelCase

Llama case:

Uppercase initial letter, first letter of each subsequent word capitalised, with no separators between words: LlamaCaseSample

Source file format

MAME C++ source files are encoded as UTF-8 text, assuming fixed-width characters, with tab stops at four-space intervals. Source files should end with a terminating end-of-line. Any valid printable Unicode text is permitted in comments. Outside comments and strings, only the printable ASCII subset of Unicode is permitted.

The srcclean tool is used to enforce file format rules before each release. You can build this tool and apply it to the files you modify before opening a pull request to avoid conflicts or surprising changes later.

Naming conventions

Preprocessor macros

Macro names should use screaming snake case. Macros are always global and name conflicts can cause confusing errors – think carefully about what macros really need to be in headers and name them carefully.

Include guards

Include guard macros should begin with MAME_, and end with a capitalised version of the file name, with separators replaced by underscores.

Constants

Constants should use screaming snake case, whether they are constant globals, constant data members, enumerators or preprocessor constants.

Functions

Free functions names should use snake case. (There are some utility function that were previously implemented as preprocessor macros that still use screaming snake case.)

Classes

Class names should use snake case. Abstract class names should end in _base. Public member functions (including static member functions) should use snake case.

Device classes

Concrete driver driver_device implementation names conventionally end in _state, while other concrete device class names end in _device. Concrete device_interface names conventionally begin with device_ and end with _interface.

Device types

Device types should use screaming snake case. Remember that device types are names in the global namespace, so choose explicit, unambiguous names.

Enumerations

The enumeration name should use snake case. The enumerators should use screaming snake case.

Template parameters

Template parameters should use llama case (both type and value parameters).

Identifiers containing two consecutive underscores or starting with an underscore followed by an uppercase letter are always reserved and should not be used.

Type names and other identifiers with a leading underscore should be avoided within the global namespace, as they are explicitly reserved according to the C++ standard. Additionally, identifiers suffixed with _t should be avoided within the global namespace, as they are also reserved according to POSIX standards. While MAME violates this policy occasionally – most notably with device_t – it’s considered to be an unfortunate legacy decision that should be avoided in any new code.

Variables and literals

Octal literals are discouraged from use outside of specific cases. They lack the obvious letter-based prefixes found in hexadecimal and binary literals, and therefore can be difficult to distinguish at a glance from a decimal literal to coders who are unfamiliar with octal notation.

Lower-case hexadecimal literals are preferred, e.g. 0xbadc0de rather than 0xBADC0DE. For clarity, try not to exceed the bit width of the variable which will be used to store it.

Binary literals have rarely been used in the MAME source code due to the 0b prefix not being standardised until C++14, but there is no policy to avoid their use.

Integer suffix notation should be used when specifying 64-bit literals, but is not strictly required in other cases. It can, however, clarify the intended use of a given literal at a glance. Uppercase long integer literal suffixes should be used to avoid confusion with the digit 1, e.g. 7LL rather than 7ll.

Digit grouping should be used for longer numeric literals, as it aids in recognising order of magnitude or bit field positions at a glance. Decimal literals should use groups of three digits, and hexadecimal literals should use groups of four digits, outside of specific situations where different grouping would be easier to understand, e.g. 4'433'619 or 0xfff8'1fff.

Types that do not have a specifically defined size should be avoided if they are to be registered with MAME’s save-state system, as it harms portability. In general, this means avoiding the use of int for these members.

It's encouraged, but not required, for class data members to be prefixed with m_ for non-static instance members and s_ for static members. This does not apply to nested classes or structs.

Bracing and indentation

Tabs are used for initial indentation of lines, with one tab used per nested scope level. Statements split across multiple lines should be indented by two tabs. Spaces are used for alignment at other places within a line.

Either K&R or Allman-style bracing is preferred. There is no specific preference for bracing on single-line statements, although bracing should be consistent for a given if/else block, as shown:

if (x == 0)
{
    return;
}
else
{
    call_some_function();
    x--;
}

When using a series of if/else or if/else if/else blocks with comments at the top indentation level, avoid extraneous newlines. The use of additional newlines may lead to else if or else blocks being missed due to the newlines pushing the blocks outside the visible editor height:

// Early-out if our hypothetical counter has run out.
if (x == 0)
{
    return;
}
// We should do something if the counter is running.
else
{
    call_some_function();
    x--;
}

Indentation for case statements inside a switch body can either be on the same level as the switch statement or inward by one level. There is no specific style which is used across all core files, although indenting by one level appears to be used most often.

Spacing

Consistent single-spacing between binary operators, variables, and literals is strongly preferred. The following examples exhibit reasonably consistent spacing:

uint8_t foo = (((bar + baz) + 3) & 7) << 1;
uint8_t foo = ((bar << 1) + baz) & 0x0e;
uint8_t foo = bar ? baz : 5;

The following examples exhibit extremes in either direction, although having extra spaces is less difficult to read than having too few:

uint8_t foo = ( ( ( bar + baz ) + 3 ) & 7 ) << 1;
uint8_t foo = ((bar<<1)+baz)&0x0e;
uint8_t foo = (bar?baz:5);

A space should be used between a fundamental C++ statement and its opening parenthesis, e.g.:

switch (value) ...
if (a != b) ...
for (int i = 0; i < foo; i++) ...

Scoping

Variables should be scoped as narrowly as is reasonably possible. There are many instances of C89-style local variable declaration in the MAME codebase, but this is largely a hold-over from MAME’s early days, which pre-date the C99 specification.

The following two snippets exhibit the legacy style of local variable declaration, followed by the more modern and preferred style:

void example_device::some_function()
{
    int i;
    uint8_t data;

    for (i = 0; i < std::size(m_buffer); i++)
    {
        data = m_buffer[i];
        if (data)
        {
            some_other_function(data);
        }
    }
}

void example_device::some_function()
{
    for (int i = 0; i < std::size(m_buffer); i++)
    {
        const uint8_t data = m_buffer[i];
        if (data)
        {
            some_other_function(data);
        }
    }
}

Enumerated values, structs, and classes used only by one specific device should be declared within the device's class itself. This avoids pollution of the global namespace and makes the device-specific use of them more obvious at a glance.

Const Correctness

Const-correctness has not historically been a strict requirement of code that goes into MAME, but there’s increasing value in it as the amount of code refactoring increases and technical debt decreases.

When writing new code, it’s worth taking the time to determine if a local variable can be declared const. Similarly, it's encouraged to consider which member functions of a new class can be const qualified.

In a similar vein, arrays of constants should be declared constexpr and should use screaming snake case, as outlined towards the top of this document. Lastly, arrays of C-style strings should be declared as both a const array of const strings, as so:

static const char *const EXAMPLE_NAMES[4] =
{
    "1-bit",
    "2-bit",
    "4-bit",
    "Invalid"
};

Comments

While /* ANSI C comments */ are often found in the codebase, there has been a gradual shift towards // C++-style comments for single-line comments. This is very much a guideline, and coders are encouraged to use whichever style is most comfortable.

Unless specifically quoting content from a machine or ancillary materials, comments should be in English so as to match the predominant language that the MAME team shares worldwide.

Commented-out code should typically be removed prior to authoring a pull request, as it has a tendency to rot due to the fast-moving nature of MAME’s core API. If there is a desire known beforehand for the code to eventually be included, it should be bookended in if (0) or if (false), as code removed through a preprocessor macro will rot at the same rate.

MAME-Specific Helpers

When at all possible, use helper functions and macros for bit manipulation operations.

The BIT(value, bit) helper can be used to extract the state of a bit at a given position from an integer value. The resulting value will be aligned to the least significant bit position, i.e. will be either 0 or 1.

An overload of the same function, BIT(value, bit, width) can be used to extract a bit field of a specified width from an integer value, starting at the specified bit position. The result will also be right-justified and will be of the same type as the incoming value.

There are, additionally, a number of helpers for functionality such as counting leading zeroes/ones, population count, and signed/unsigned integer multiplication and division for both 32-bit and 64-bit results. Not all of these helpers have wide use in the MAME codebase, but using them in new code is strongly preferred when that code is performance- critical, as they utilise inline assembly or compiler intrinsics per- platform when available.

count_leading_zeros_32/64(T value)

Accepts an unsigned 32/64-bit value and returns an unsigned 8-bit value containing the number of consecutive zeros starting from the most significant bit.

count_leading_ones_32/64(T value)

Same functionality as above, but examining consecutive one-bits.

population_count_32/64(T value)

Accepts an unsigned 32/64-bit value and returns the number of one-bits found, i.e. the Hamming weight of the value.

rotl_32/64(T value, int shift)

Performs a circular/barrel left shift of an unsigned 32/64-bit value with the specified shift value. The shift value will be masked to the valid bit range for a 32-bit or 64-bit value.

rotr_32/64(T value, int shift)

Same functionality as above, but with a right shift.

For documentation on helpers related to multiplication and division, refer to src/osd/eminline.h.

Logging

MAME has multiple logging function for different purposes. Two of the most frequently used logging functions are logerror and osd_printf_verbose:

Devices inherit a logerror member function. This automatically includes the fully-qualified tag of the invoking device in log messages. Output is sent to MAME’s debugger’s rotating log buffer if the debugger is enabled. If the -log option is enabled, it’s also written to the file error.log in the working directory. If the -oslog option is enabled, it’s additionally sent to the OS diagnostic output (the host debugger diagnostic log on Windows if a host debugger is attached, or standard error otherwise).

The output of the osd_printf_verbose function is sent to standard error if the -verbose option is enabled.

The osd_printf_verbose function should be used for logging that is useful for diagnosing user issues, while logerror should be used for messages more relevant to developers (either developing MAME itself, or developing software for emulated systems using MAME’s debugger).

For debug logging, a channel-based logging system exists via the header logmacro.h. It can be used as a generic logging system as follows, without needing to make use of its ability to mask out specific channels:

// All other headers in the .cpp file should be above this line.
#define VERBOSE (1)
#include "logmacro.h"
...
void some_device::some_reg_write(u8 data)
{
    LOG("%s: some_reg_write: %02x\n", machine().describe_context(), data);
}

The above example also makes use of a helper function which is available in all derivatives of device_t: machine().describe_context(). This function will return a string that describes the emulation context in which the function is being run. This includes the fully-qualified tag of the currently executing device (if any). If the relevant device implements device_state_interface, it will also include the current program-counter value reported by the device.

For more fine-grained control, specific bit masks can be defined and used via the LOGMASKED macro:

// All other headers in the .cpp file should be above this line.
#define LOG_FOO (1 << 1U)
#define LOG_BAR (1 << 2U)

#define VERBOSE (LOG_FOO | LOG_BAR)
#include "logmacro.h"
...
void some_device::some_reg_write(u8 data)
{
    LOGMASKED(LOG_FOO, "some_reg_write: %02x\n", data);
}

void some_device::another_reg_write(u8 data)
{
    LOGMASKED(LOG_BAR, "another_reg_write: %02x\n", data);
}

Note that the least significant bit position for user-supplied masks is 1, as bit position 0 is reserved for LOG_GENERAL.

By default, LOG and LOGMASKED will use the device-supplied logerror function. However, this can be redirected as desired. The most common use case would be to direct output to the standard output instead, which can be accomplished by explicitly defining LOG_OUTPUT_FUNC as so:

#define LOG_OUTPUT_FUNC osd_printf_info

A developer should always ensure that VERBOSE is set to 0 and that any definition of LOG_OUTPUT_FUNC is commented out prior to opening a pull request.

Structural organization

All C++ source files must begin with a two comments listing the distribution license and copyright holders in a standard format. Licenses are specified by their SPDX short identifier if available. Here is an example of the standard format:

// license:BSD-3-Clause
// copyright-holders:David Haywood, Tomasz Slanina

Header includes should generally be grouped from most-dependent to least-dependent, and sorted alphabetically within said groups:

The project prefix header, emu.h, must be the first thing in a translation unit

Local project headers (i.e. headers found in the same source directory)

Headers in src/devices

Headers in src/emu

Headers in src/lib/formats

Headers in src/lib/util

Headers from the OSD layer

C++ standard library headers

C standard library headers

OS-specific headers

Layout headers

Finally, task-specific headers such as logmacro.h - described in the previous section - should be included last. A practical example follows:

#include "emu.h"

#include "cpu/m68000/m68000.h"
#include "machine/mc68328.h"
#include "machine/ram.h"
#include "sound/dac.h"
#include "video/mc68328lcd.h"
#include "video/sed1375.h"

#include "emupal.h"
#include "screen.h"
#include "speaker.h"

#include "pilot1k.lh"

#define VERBOSE (0)
#include "logmacro.h"

In most cases, the class declaration for a system driver should be within the corresponding source file along with the implementation. In such cases, the class declaration and all contents of the source file, excluding the GAME, COMP, or CONS macro, should be enclosed in an anonymous namespace (this produces better compiler diagnostics, allows more aggressive optimisation, reduces the chance of duplicate symbols, and reduces linking time).

Within a class declaration, there should be one section for each member access level (public, protected and private) if practical. This may not be possible in cases where private constants and/or types need to be declared before public members. Members should use the least public access level necessary. Overridden virtual member functions should generally use the same access level as the corresponding member function in the base class.

Class member declarations should be grouped to aid understanding:

Within a member access level section, constants, types, data members, instance member functions and static member functions should be grouped.

In device classes, configuration member functions should be grouped separately from live signal member functions.

Overridden virtual member functions should be grouped according to the base classes they are inherited from.

For classes with multiple overloaded constructors, constructor delegation should be used where possible to avoid repeated member initialiser lists.

Constants which are used by a device or machine driver should be in the form of explicitly-sized enumerated values within the class declaration, or be relegated to #define macros within the source file. This helps avoid polluting the preprocessor.

Guidelines for Software Lists

Introduction

MAME’s software lists describe known software media for emulated systems in a form that can be used to identify media image files for known software, verify media image file integrity, and load media image files for emulation. Software lists are implemented as XML files in the hash folder. The XML structure is described in the file hash/softwarelist.dtd.

Philosophically, software list items should represent the original media, rather than a specific dump of the media. Ideally, it should be possible for anyone with the media to dump it and produce the same image file. Of course, this isn’t always possible in practice – in particular it’s problematic for inherently analog media, like home computer software stored on audio tape cassettes.

MAME strives to document the best available media images. It is not our intention to propagate corrupted, truncated, defaced, watermarked, or otherwise bad media images. Where possible, file structures matching the original media structure are preferred. For example we prefer individual files for separate ROM chips in cartridge media, and we use disk images rather than archives of files extracted from the original disks.

Items and parts

A software list is a collection of items and each item may have multiple parts. An item represents a piece of software, as distributed as a complete package. A part represents a single piece of media within the package. Parts can be mounted individually in emulated media devices. For example a piece of software distributed on three floppy disks will be a single item, while each floppy disk will be one part within that item.

Sometimes, logically separate parts of a single physical piece of media are represented as separate parts within a software item. For example each side of an audio tape cassette is represented as a separate part. However individual ROM chips within a cartridge may be separate files, but they are not separate parts, as the cartridge is mounted as a whole.

Each item is a software element. The software element may have the following attributes:

name (required)

The short name identifying the item. This is used for file names, command line arguments, database keys, URL fragments, and many other purposes. It should be terse but still recognisable. It must be unique within the software list. Valid characters are lowercase English letters, decimal digits and underscores. The maximum allowed length is sixteen characters.

cloneof (optional)

The short name of the parent item if the item is a clone. The parent must be within the same software list – parent/clone relationships spanning multiple software lists are not supported.

supported (optional)

One of the values yes (fully usable in emulation), no (not usable in emulation), or partial (usable in emulation with limitations). If the attribute is not present, it is equivalent to yes. Examples of partially supported software include games that are playable with graphical glitches, and office software where some but not all functionality works.

Each part is a part element within the software element. The part element must have the following attributes:

name (required)

The short name identifying the part. This is used for command line arguments, database keys, URL fragments, and many other purposes. It must be unique within the item. It is also used as the display name if a separate display name is not provided. Valid characters are lowercase English letters, decimal digits and underscores. The maximum allowed length is sixteen characters.

interface (required)

This attribute is used to identify suitable emulated media devices for mounting the software part. Applicable values depend on the emulated system.

Metadata

Software lists support various kinds of metadata. All software list items require the following metadata elements to be present:

description

This is the primary display name for the software item. It should be the original name of the software, transliterated into English Latin script if necessary. It must be unique within the software list. If extra text besides the title itself is required for disambiguation, use lowercase outside of proper nouns, initialisms and verbatim quotes.

year

The year of release or copyright year for the software. If unknown, use an estimate with a question mark. Items can be filtered by year in the software selection menu.

publisher

The publisher of the software. This may be the same as the developer if the software was self-published. Items can be filtered by published in the software selection menu.

Most user-visible software item metadata is provided using info elements. Each info element must have a name attribute and a value attribute. The name attribute identifies the type of metadata, and the value attribute is the metadata value itself. Note that name attributes do not need to be unique within an item. Multiple info elements with the same name may be present if appropriate. This is frequently seen for software sold using different titles in different regions.

Prefer multiple info elements with the same name attribute over combining multiple values into a single element. For example if a piece of software supports multiple user interface languages, use multiple info elements with name="language" attributes. This makes filtering and database queries more practical.

MAME displays metadata from info elements in the software selection menu. The following name attributes are recognised specifically, and can show localised names:

alt_title

Used for alternate titles. Examples are different tiles used in different languages, scripts or regions, or different titles used on the title screen and packaging. MAME searches alternate titles as well as the description.

author

Author of the software. Items can be filtered by author in the software selection menu.

barcode

Barcode number identifying the software package (typically an EAN).

developer

Developer responsible for implementing the software. Items can be filtered by developer in the software selection menu.

distributor

Party responsible for distributing the software to retailers (or customers in the case of direct sales). Items can be filtered by distributor in the software selection menu.

install

Installation instructions.

isbn

ISBN for software included with a commercial book.

language

User interface language supported by the software.

oem

Original equipment manufacturer, typically used with customised versions of software distributed by a hardware vendor.

original_publisher

The original publisher, for items representing software re-released by a different publisher.

partno

Distributor’s part number for the software.

pcb

Printed circuit board identifier, typically for cartridge media.

programmer

Programmer who wrote the code for the software.

release

Fine-grained release date for the software, if known. Use YYYYMMDD format with no punctuation. If only the month is known, use “xx” for the day digits. For example 199103xx or 19940729.

serial

Number identifying the software within a series of releases.

usage

Usage instructions.

version

Version number of the software.

Contributing to MAME

So you want to contribute to MAME but aren’t sure where to start? Well the great news is that there’s always plenty to do for people with a variety of skill sets.

Testing and reporting bugs

One thing MAME can always do with is more testing and bug reports. If you’re familiar with a system that MAME emulates and notice something wrong, or if you find a bug in MAME’s user interface, you can head over to MAME Testers [https://mametesters.org/] and, assuming it isn’t already reported, register an account and open an issue. Be sure to read the FAQ [https://mametesters.org/faq.html] and rules [https://mametesters.org/rules.html] first to ensure you start out on the right foot. Please note that MAME Testers only accepts user-facing bugs in tagged release versions.

For other kinds of issues, we have GitHub Issues [https://github.com/mamedev/mame/issues/]. There’s a bit more leeway here. For example we accept developer-facing issues (e.g. bugs in internal APIs, or build system inadequacies), feature requests, and major regressions before they make it into a released version. Please respect the fact that the issue tracker is not a discussion or support forum, it’s only for reporting reproducible issues. Don’t open issues to ask questions or request support. Also, keep in mind that the master branch is unstable. If the current revision doesn’t compile at all or is completely broken, we’re probably already aware of it and don’t need issues opened for that. Wait a while and see if there’s an update. You might want to comment on the commit in question with the compiler error message, particularly if you’re compiling in an unorthodox but supported configuration.

When opening an issue, remember to provide as much information as possible to help others understand, reproduce, and diagnose the issue. Things that are helpful to include:

The incorrect behaviour, and expected or correct behaviour. Be specific: just saying it “doesn’t work” usually isn’t enough detail.

Environment details, including your operating system, CPU architecture, system locale, and display language, if applicable. For video output bugs, note your video hardware (GPU), driver version, and the MAME video output module you’re using. For input handling bugs, include the input peripherals and MAME input modules you’re using.

The exact version of MAME you’re using, including a git commit digest if it isn’t a tagged release version, and any non-standard build options.

The exact system and software being emulated (may not be applicable for issues with parts of MAME’s UI, like the system selection menu). Include things like the selected BIOS version, and emulated peripheral (slot device) configuration.

Steps to reproduce the issue. Assume the person reading is familiar with MAME itself, but not necessarily familiar with the emulated system and software in question. For emulation issues, input recordings and/or saved state files for reproducing the issue can be invaluable.

An original reference for the correct behaviour. If you have access to the original hardware for the emulated system, it helps to make a recording of the correct behaviour for comparison.

Contributing to MAME’s source code

MAME itself is written in C++, but that isn’t the sum total of the source code. The source code also includes:

The documentation hosted on this site (and also included in releases as a PDF), written in reStructuredText [https://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/master/usage/restructuredtext/basics.html] markup.

The supplied plugins, written in Lua 5.3 [https://www.lua.org/manual/5.3/].

Internal layouts for emulated machines that need to display more than a simple video screen. These are an XML application described here.

The software lists, describing known software media for systems that MAME emulates. MAME software lists are an XML application.

The user interface translations, in GNU gettext PO format. They can be edited with a good text editor, or a dedicated tool like Poedit [https://poedit.net/].

Our primary source code repository is hosted on GitHub [https://github.com/mamedev/mame/]. We prefer to receive source code contributions in the form of pull requests [https://github.com/mamedev/mame/pulls]. You’ll need to learn the basics of git distributed version control and familiarise yourself with the git tools. The basic process for creating a pull request is as follows:

Sign up for an account on GitHub.

Create a fork of the mamedev/mame repository.

Create a new branch off the master branch in your forked repository.

Clone your forked repository, and check out your new branch.

Make your changes, and build and test them locally.

Commit your changes, and push your branch to GitHub.

Optionally enable GitHub Actions for your forked repository, allowing your changes to be built on Windows, macOS and Linux.

Open a pull request to merge your changes into the master branch in the mamedev/mame repository.

Please keep the following in mind (note that not all points are relevant to all kinds of changes):

Make your commit messages descriptive. Please include what the change affects, and what it’s supposed to achieve. A person reading the commit log shouldn’t need to resort to examining the diff to get a basic idea of what a commit is supposed to do. The default commit messages provided by GitHub are completely useless, as they don’t give any indication of what a change is supposed to do.

Test your changes. Ensure that a full build of MAME completes, and that the code you changed works. It’s a good idea to build with DEBUG=1 to check that assertions compile and don’t trigger.

Use an enlightening pull request title and description. The title should give a one-line summary of what the overall change affects and what it’s supposed to do. The description should contain more detail. Don’t leave the description empty and describe the change in comments, as this makes searching and filtering more difficult.

Be aware that GitHub Actions has opaque resource limits. It isn’t clear when you’re close to the limits, and we’ve had contributors banned from GitHub Actions for violating the limits. Even if you appeal the ban, they still won’t tell you what the actual limits are, justifying this by saying that if you know the limits, you can take steps to evade them. If you enable GitHub Actions, consider not pushing individual commits if you don’t need them to be automatically built, or cancelling workflow runs when you don’t need the results.

If your submission is a computer or other device such as a synthesizer or sampler which requires a disk, tape, cartridge, or other media to start up and run, please consider creating a software list containing at least one example of that media. This helps everyone making changes to shared MAME components to easily verify if the changes negatively impact your code.

When submitting any new non-arcade machine, but especially a machine which does not auto-boot and requires some interaction to start up and be usable, consider adding usage instructions to the System-Specific Setup and Information [https://wiki.mamedev.org/index.php/System-Specific_Setup_and_Information] page of the MAME Wiki [https://wiki.mamedev.org]. Anyone can edit the wiki after creating an account, and sub-pages for your system which discuss technical details of the system are also welcome.

We have guidelines for specific parts of the source:

C++ Coding Guidelines
Guidelines for Software Lists